<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Richmond Lab</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Richmond Lab</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>open science I</title>
      <link>/post/open-science-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/open-science-i/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;open-science-in-psychology&#34;&gt;Open Science in Psychology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Open science” is a buzzword becoming increasingly heard in the academic sphere – in university courses and at conferences. But what is open science?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This term at lab meeting, we are reading and discussing a selection of papers related to the Open Science movement. We are focussing on the 3 P’s of Open Science: Philosophy, Politics and Practicalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can check out our Open Science &lt;a href=&#34;insert link&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;reading list here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far we have learned a lot about how the Open Science movement came about as well as the benefits and challenges of practicing open science, especially in our subfields (developmental/clinical) of Psychology. Below details some of our thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-open-science&#34;&gt;What is Open Science?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, open science is about being transparent about what we do and what we find as scientists. This includes sharing methodology, stimuli, code and data. Practicing open science makes it more likely that our work is reproducible and able to be replicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big part of being transparent involves pre-registering our intentions for data analysis and reporting findings in a way that is true to that intent; that is, not reporting only significant results. Open science is also about making results as available to the public as you can, as early as possible (e.g., preprints).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two quotes from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/349/6251/aac4716&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Open Science Collaboration (2015)&lt;/a&gt; nicely encapsulate the philosophical stance of the Open Science movement and subsequent good research practices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Scientific process is a cumulative process of uncertainty reduction that can only succeed if science itself remains the greatest skeptic of its explanatory claims&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Innovation points out paths that are possible; replication points out paths that are likely; progress relies on both&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-did-the-open-science-movement-come-about&#34;&gt;How did the Open Science movement come about?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/349/6251/aac4716&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Open Science Collaboration’s (2015)&lt;/a&gt; article seems like the “reality check” paper for the Psychology research world. All of us in the lab could recall this paper being published and its ripple effects, which led to much needed attention being drawn to how psychology research should be conducted – i.e., in-line with core philosophy of science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to be credible, research has to be reproducible. And many studies selected for the Open Science Collaboration were not found to have reproducible findings. The ripple effects of this ‘reproducibility crisis’ called into action the Open Science movement, which is advocating for research practices that will improve the reproducibility of research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-are-the-benefits-of-practising-open-science&#34;&gt;What are the benefits of practising Open Science?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;1-greater-faith-in-research&#34;&gt;1. Greater faith in research&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Open Science movement should help improve the reliability and quality of scientific work. For example, pre-registration helps ensure that researchers have fully considered analyses and anticipated outcomes of an experiment. Pre-registrations transparently differentiate between confirmatory hypothesis testing and post-hoc exploratory analyses. This helps to guard against questionable research practices and unconscious errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Registered Reports take it one step further. In RR, hypotheses and methods are peer-reviewed and an author can obtain in principle acceptance for publication prior to data collection. This also helps prevent questionable research practices but also importantly improves chances of publication, in the case of null findings. The reporting of null findings is important because in well-designed and powered experiments, these findings are still informative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;tips&#34;&gt;Tips&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adopting Open Science procedures now will likely be looked on favourably in the future. Make your work accessible as possible and pre-register experiments when suitable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t be afraid of designing experiments where null findings may occur.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consult the material provided by the Centre for Open Science when preparing preregistration or registered reports.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t sit around and complain about the quality or reliability of research – do something about it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;2-new-helpful-systems&#34;&gt;2. New Helpful Systems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open and reproducible science can help researchers and promote collaboration. It is possible to build up well documented and robust code libraries that may be reused for future projects and for teaching purposes. If everyone shares, you can gain access to free, high-quality, and  often standardized data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;tips-1&#34;&gt;Tips&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make use of new tools that facilitate sharing and documenting your work efficiently and publicly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;think about whether your research question can be addressed with existing, open data sets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;take advantage of free training options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;select methods that fit your research question with feasibility in mind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-investment-in-your-future&#34;&gt;3. Investment in your future&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting work and data in the public domain is central to open science and doing so may increase ECRs’ opportunities for acknowledgement, exchange, collaboration and advancement. Preprints allow you get the word out about your research earlier and will often get media coverage. Early adoption of open and reproducible methods is an investment in the future and can put young researchers ahead of the curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-are-the-challenges-of-practicing-open-science&#34;&gt;What are the challenges of practicing Open Science?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;1-restrictions-on-flexibility&#34;&gt;1. Restrictions on flexibility&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hypothesis can only be held before the data are looked at, usually before the data are collected. Open science methods respect the distinction between exploratory analyses from planned confirmatory hypothesis testing.
When data collection has started, new learning about analysis techniques, subsequent publications and exploration of patterns in data cannot inform confirmatory hypothesis or the preregistered experimental design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;tips-2&#34;&gt;Tips&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pilot data are your friend; you can explore without constraint&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make a distinction between planned and exploratory analyses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;preregistred and RR experiments are likely to have a higher evidential value than closed science experiments in the future and so researchers should be encouraged to use these formats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be open to mistakes and do not reprimand others for their mistakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;2-the-time-cost&#34;&gt;2. The time cost&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no argument that Open Science takes longer. Archiving, documenting, and maintaining quality control over code and data takes time. The preregistration and RR process also take time; it is important to carefully consider the research strategy as early as possible in projects, because resources (generally, but particularly time) are limited for ECRs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;tip&#34;&gt;Tip&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;preregistered, well powered experiments are preferential to those that are not, but it should be expected and planned for that these will take longer than would otherwise be the case.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;take time cost into account, both in planning research and thinking about employment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-incentive-structures-aren-t-in-place-yet&#34;&gt;3. Incentive structures aren&amp;rsquo;t  in place yet&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We talked about this point for a long time in our lab meeting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systems that reward open science practices are currently rare. High-profile journals are more likely to publish papers that report positive results and tell a &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; (aka tidy) story.  Preregistration and the loss of flexibility that goes with it limits the extent to which articles can be finessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The requirement for studies to be novel, can also work againest motivations to perform replications. In lab meeting, we talked about how the innovation motivation goes all the way back to how we teach research methods to undergraduates. When teaching students about  writing, we emphasise how important it is to highlight how the project fills a gap in the literature. We seldom talk about value of replication and extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within open science, standards are still developing. There are practical concerns around power and whether in certain subfields (infancy, for example) it is feasible to run high-powered studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are risks for those at all levels of the game, particularly when the motivation of late has been quantity over quality. For ECRs, engaging in open science is likely to result in fewer publications, which could be quesitoned once you go on the job market. For senior researchers, while it is possible that their previous work could be devalued by failed replications, they are likely to have already secured the benefits of quicker and less robust research practices. Those who are PhD advisors and on hiring committeess, may teach and expect levels of &amp;ldquo;productivity&amp;rdquo; from a different time, which is likely to become a source of tension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;tip-1&#34;&gt;Tip&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Early adoption of open methods and high standards requires careful planning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;engaging in OS should put ECRs ahead of the curve as practices evolve&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be strategic with which open science practices suit your research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on quality over quantity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given credit to others for efforts made toward the common good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;further-thoughts-from-a-ecr-perspective&#34;&gt;Further thoughts from a ECR perspective:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tips in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3000246&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Allen &amp;amp; Mehler (2019)&lt;/a&gt; paper weren&amp;rsquo;t terribly reassuring in regard to the time problem. Doing open science takes time, something that ECRs just don’t have. Not only are PhD programs and post doc fellowships short, moving institutions and getting a lab going slows you down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There needs to be a culture shift and we see conflict is inevitable. Is this movement overly optimistic?? Until the incentives really move, that is open science practice is valued on hiring/promotion committees and in funding applications, this shift could move really slowly, disadvantaging the new but leaving the old unaffected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;are-there-field-specific-challenges&#34;&gt;Are there field-specific challenges?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clinical: There are so many iterations to therapy models. While this is helpful in terms of allowing adaptations to better fit the needs of individuals, replication is uncommon, unless it’s the same team of individuals testing the same intervention. Clinical trials are also very expensive and not funded well. It comes back to progress needing to be a balance of innovation and replication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developmental: Research with infants and young children is slow. Recruitment is difficult and even when you get babies to the lab they sometimes &amp;ldquo;fuss out&amp;rdquo;. It is really hard to get the kind of large samples that open science practitioners are talking about. &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1745691616689062&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hamlin (2017)&lt;/a&gt; made a good point in her article that open science will only work if it is inclusive and best practices are designed for everyone. The big replication projects like Many Babies are one way to go about it, but it is important that developmental psychology forges its place in the movement. It was great to see this week that an Open Science workshop is planned for the Cognitive Development Society conference in Louisville KT later in the year. Normalising Open Science for everyone is key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Our &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/cogdevsoc?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@cogdevsoc&lt;/a&gt; preconference  on open developmental science has a website! Take a look at our fantastic line up &amp;amp; schedule &amp;amp; get info on how to register. Worth the trip to Louisville, KY! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/etWNqEUc2A&#34;&gt;https://t.co/etWNqEUc2A&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Sabine Doebel (@sabine_doebel) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sabine_doebel/status/1144590901047488512?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 28, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>reading list</title>
      <link>/post/reading-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/reading-list/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Here is the list of Open Science reading that we are working our way through at lab meeting this term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;week-0&#34;&gt;Week 0&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Munafò, M. R., Nosek, B. A., Bishop, D. V., Button, K. S., Chambers, C. D., Du Sert, N. P., &amp;hellip; &amp;amp; Ioannidis, J. P. (2017). A manifesto for reproducible science. &lt;em&gt;Nature human behaviour&lt;/em&gt;, 1(1), 0021. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-016-0021.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spellman, B. A. (2015). A short (personal) future history of revolution 2.0. &lt;em&gt;Perspectives on Psychological Science&lt;/em&gt;, 10(6), 886–899 &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/pdf/10.1177/1745691615609918?casa_token=GwWkc-30de4AAAAA:T99zylgrQfNG2eYAbv2Rgpi06e3AsaK2JtkiWSXCG31gWk3Ca5eNkX-nrGhy0ocuB-R23ECh9C1MZA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamlin, J. K. (2017). Is psychology moving in the right direction? An analysis of the evidentiary value movement. &lt;em&gt;Perspectives on Psychological Science&lt;/em&gt;, 12(4), 690-693. &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1745691616689062&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;week-1&#34;&gt;Week 1&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open Science Collaboration. (2015). Estimating the reproducibility of psychological science. &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;, 349(6251), aac4716. &lt;a href=&#34;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/349/6251/aac4716&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allen, C., &amp;amp; Mehler, D. M. (2019). Open science challenges, benefits and tips in early career and beyond. &lt;em&gt;PLoS biology&lt;/em&gt;, 17(5), e3000246. &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3000246&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;week-2&#34;&gt;Week 2&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spellman, B. A., Gilbert, E. A., &amp;amp; Corker, K. S. (2018). Open science. &lt;em&gt;Stevens&amp;rsquo; Handbook of Experimental Psychology and Cognitive Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt;, 5, 1-47. &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/psyarxiv/ak6jr/download&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;week-4&#34;&gt;Week 4&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Klein, O., Hardwicke, T. E., Aust, F., Breuer, J., Danielsson, H., Mohr, A. H., &amp;hellip; &amp;amp; Frank, M. C. (2018). A practical guide for transparency in psychological science. &lt;em&gt;Collabra: Psychology&lt;/em&gt;, 4(1) &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.collabra.org/articles/10.1525/collabra.158/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
